Albert Schweitzer Papers
Albert Schweitzer Papers
- Writings
  - Notebooks
    - [untitled], 1939; notes from two voyages (to and from Europe) and from a sojourn in Alsace, including information about supplies ordered; poems; notes on correspondence; clippings; lists of contributors; comments about the imminent outbreak of war in Europe (Box 10)
    - "Calculs de la déclarations de l'impôt sur la revenu", 1940-1955; customs forms; lists of supplies (Box 10)
    - [untitled], 1940; addresses; notes on correspondence, medical and personnel matters; expenditures; remarks about the war, including an extensive description of the 20 day seige of Lambaréné (Box 11)
    - "Cahier des Editeurs 1941_1942_1943_1944_1953", 1941-1944; addresses of editors, with notes about financial agreements (Box 11)
    - [untitled], 1941; addresses; a description of life at Lambaréné, including Hélène Schweitzer's arrival; quotes; recipes; notes on personnel matters; remarks about astronomy and gardening (Box 11)
    - "Medizinische Notizen Heft III", 1942; medical notes 1942 list of hospital personnel; poems; quotes; recipes; notes on medical issues; addresses, with comments about people; a review of the year 1942 (Box 11)
    - [untitled], 1943; list of hospital personnel; poems; quotes; recipes; reminiscences; addresses, with comments about people; thoughts about religion; clippings; a review of the year 1943 (Box 11)
    - [untitled], 1944; notes on daily events; addresses; recipes; personnel matters; quotes; remarks about the American capture of Strassburg; comments about a will; a review of the year 1944 (Box 11)
    - [untitled], 1945; notes on daily events at Lambaréné; comments about the end of the war; notes on correspondence (Box 11)
    - "Déclaration de Revenues 1946_1947_1948_1949_1950_1951_1952_1953_1954", 1946-1954; income tax returns (Box 11)
    - "Medizinische Notizen Heft IV", 1946-1950; medical notes 1946 addresses; excerpts from correspondence; poems; recipes; notes about Jean Paul Sartre and about the Strassbourg-Basel railroad line; lecture notes; clippings; a review of the year 1946 (Box 11)
    - "11 Adresses importants 21 lettres à ecrire", 1947-1948; 1953-1954; addresses and notes about correspondence to be answered (Box 12)
    - [untitled], 1947; addresses; notes on books; quotes; poems; clippings; comments about construction projects at Lambaréné (Box 12)
    - "Reise Schweiz 2_11_48", 1948; addresses, with comments about people (Box 12)
    - [untitled], 1948; notes about daily events and politics; addresses; comments about people and correspondence; historical dates in African history; history of the Schweitzer family; poems; lecture invitations; concert programs (Box 12)
    - "Voyage en Amérique 22_6_49", 1949; addresses; comments about people; and other notes from the U.S. trip (Box 12)
    - "Voyage en Amérique 22_6_1949 Günsbach Alsace", notes about the U.S. trip; lists of addresses (Box 12)
    - "Voyage Scandinavie-Hollande 8_9_1949", notes about the trip through Scandinavia and the Netherlands; addresses; timetables; comments about people (Box 12)
    - "Paris octobre 1949", short notes; addresses from the trip to Paris (Box 12)
    - "Départ 28 octobre 1949 Brazza pour Lambaréné", addresses; short notes (Box 12)
    - "Voyage Suisse 1949", addresses, with comments about people; other notes from the trip to Switzerland (Box 12)
    - Daily events in Alsace, 1949; notes about Bach and Goethe in preparation for the U.S. trip; addresses; poems; quotes; excerpts from letters; comments on books (Box 12)
    - A diary from Lambaréné, 1950; including comments on greetings for Schweitzer's 75th birthday; names of candidates for Lambaréné; quotes; clippings; historical notes; recipes; a list of authors and actors banned from East Germany (Box 12)
    - "Voyage Lambaréné-Günsbach par Foucauld quittant Bordeaux le 19 juin 51", 1951; notes from the trip to Europe, including addresses; a list of baggage; a detailed description of the voyage (Box 12)
    - "Frankfurt 16_9_51", 1951; mostly a list of addresses (Box 12)
    - "Paris 22_9_51", 1951; short notes on schedules and people (Box 12)
    - A diary from Lambaréné, 1951; including notes about medical issues, politics, and religion; excerpts from letters about book and recording contracts; comments about the Albert Schweitzer Fellowship; clippings; various notes from the trip to Europe (Box 12)
    - "Voyage Bordeaux - Lambaréné sur Foucauld. Départ 28_11_52", 1952; notes form the voyage, including information about people, addresses, and a list of baggage (Box 13)
    - "Voyage Lambaréné - Alsace par Foucauld 5-23 juillet 1952", notes from the voyage, including a list of baggage, the names of the crew (Box 13)
    - "Liste der im Jahre 1952 beantworteten Briefe", a list of letters answered in 1952 (Box 13)
    - "Paris 1952", names; addresses; comments about people (Box 13)
    - [untitled], 1952; notes on daily events; orders; excerpts from books; poems; timetables; comments about people (Box 13)
    - "Medizinische Notizen", 1953; medical notes (Box 13)
    - [untitled], 1953; addresses; notes about daily events at Lambaréné and in the world; quotes; notes on medical issues and personnel matters; orders; comments about correspondence. Also included are Schweitzer's comments about the message from the Nobel committee notifying him of his selection as recipient of the Peace Prize (Box 13)
    - "cahiers spéciaux des calculs des Revenus en: 1954_1955_1956_1957_1958_1959_1960_1961_1962_1963_1964_1965.", 1954-1965; a list of income by year (Box 13)
    - "Affaire Réduction Impôts des Français en USA à 15% calculs à présenter lettre Paris 18 sept.", 1954-1958; records of income in the United States (Box 13)
    - "Oslo 1954", addresses (Box 13)
    - "Général LeClerc - Voyage Günsbach - Lambaréné. Embarquement 10 déc. 1954. Port-Gentil 27 déc. 54", notes from the voyage, including a list of baggage 1955 "Voyage Angleterre automne 1955" addresses, with comments about people (Box 13)
    - "Voyage Paris automne 1955", notes from the trip to Paris and Switzerland (Box 13)
    - "Cahier 1955" an extensive diary, including poems, reminiscences, notes about medical issues and incoming letters (Box 13)
    - "Notes médicales 1956_1957_1958. Et Esquires de Commandes", 1956-1958; orders for medical supplies (Box 14)
    - "Commandes et envois de sont genre attendées et arrivés", 1956-1957; addresses, with comments about people (Box 14)
    - [untitled], 1956; extensive diary with personal thoughts and poems (Box 14)
    - "Voyage Lambaréné - Bordeaux sur Brazza 2-20 aôut 1957", notes from the voyage to Europe, including addresses; a list of baggage (Box 14)
    - "Voyage Bordeaux - Lambaréné déc. 1957 Brazza", travel documents; a baggage list (Box 14)
    - "Lambaréné 1957", addresses, with comments about people (Box 14)
    - "Voyages en 1957", addresses, with comments about people (Box 14)
    - [untitled], 1957; addresses, with comments about people; notes on daily events and personnel matters; clippings with notes about atomic testing issues; financial records; excerpts from correspondence (Box 14)
    - "Devant liste des lettres pressées", 1958-1959; addresses; excerpts from correspondence; a list of exchange rates for various currencies (Box 15)
    - [untitled], 1958; addresses; excerpts from correspondence; notes on daily events (Box 15)
    - [untitled], 1958; extensive notebook from Lambaréné, with clippings; comments on current events and history; notes on personnel and patients; poems; excerpts from correspondence (Box 15)
    - "Voyage en Europe de aôut à fin novembre", 1959; addresses; schedule; a list of baggage; comments about people and accommodations (Box 15)
    - "Voyage Bordeaux - Port Gentil sur Général Leclerc 9 dec.-27 dec. 1959", a list of baggage; some comments on people (Box 15)
    - "Cahier 1959", addresses; clippings with comments (Box 15)
    - "Notices 1959", clippings, with comments on a wide variety of subjects (Box 15)
    - "Zeitungsnachrichten und gedanken über Atom problem", 1959; notes on world events; clippings, with comments (Box 16)
    - [untitled], 1959; notes on daily events; addresses, with comments about people (Box 16)
    - [untitled], 1959; (cover missing) clippings, with a few comments (Box 16)
    - [untitled], 1960; addresses; comments about people and contributions (Box 17)
    - [untitled], 1960; mostly clippings, with comments (Box 17)
    - "Atom. nouvelles sur la question", 1961; clippings, with comments (Box 17)
    - "Cahier 1961", clippings, with comments; quotes; poems (Box 17)
    - "Lettres et affaires 1961", some clippings; notes on correspondence (Box 17)
    - "Ausschnitte in Atomsachen 1962", clippings, with comments, mostly concerning nuclear testing and the Cuban Missile Crisis (Box 17)
    - "Cahier 1962", mostly clippings, with comments (Box 18)
    - "1) Courrier 1962 2) Notices sur affaires 1962", notes on correspondence; a list of expenses (Box 18)
    - "Notizbuch für Hosentasche", 1962; addresses with comments about people; contributions (Box 18)
    - "Lettres envoyés 1963", a list of letters answered (Box 18)
    - "Nouvelles et notices Notizbuch", 1963; clippings, with comments covering a variety of subjects (Box 18)
    - "Atom Waffen Sachen und Politik", 1964; clippings, with comments (Box 18)
    - "Taschen Notizbuch", 1964; daily events; notes on correspondence and donations (Box 18)
    - "Notizbuch 1965", a few clippings, with comments (Box 18)
    - [untitled], 1965; mostly clippings, with comments; a few addresses (Box 18)
    - "Medizinische Notizen Heft II", undated; medical notes (Box 19)
    - "Medicaments Suisse", undated; list of medication available from Swiss medical supply firms (Box 19)
    - "Medicaments USA", undated; list of medication available from U.S. medical supply firms (Box 19)
  - Program notes
    - Draft of program notes for November 28, 1920 organ concert at Fraümunster, Zürich, holograph manuscript, printed program, and English translation (Box 20)
  - Scripts
    - "Albert Schweitzer", a film biography
      - Notes for director Jerome Hill (Box 20)
      - Shooting scripts with notes, 1953; undated; 3 folders (Box 20)
      - "Skizzen des Film, notizen für Erica", Oct. 26, 1953 (Box 20)
      - "Text zu den Bildern", Dec. 1954 (Box 20)
      - "Text zu den Günsbachszenen", undated (Box 20)
      - "Text zu den szenen in Günsbach", undated (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous notes, 1963; undated; 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Sermons
    - Lambaréné, Jun. 22-Sept. 28, 1930 (Box 20)
  - Short Story
    - "Moderne Berufe - der Wanzenzüchter", undated (Box 20)
  - Speeches
    - "Goethe als Denker und Mensch" (Box 20)
    - "Message pour la centenaire/ de deBrazza/ de la naissance fêté à Alger le 15 fevrier ", 1952 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Der Stromschnellen-Fetisch von Theodor Steimen" (Box 20)
    - "Meddelanden från Professor Albert Schweitzer", 1928; 1945 (Box 20)
    - Notes on atomic weapons testing and disarmament, 1960; 1961,; undated; 9 folders (Box 20)
- Memorabilia
  - Selected list of memorabilia (Box 21)
  - Artwork
    - Watercolor painting "Le Docteur Schweitzer et Monsieur Eckert devant la maison à Gunsbach" by Gloria Coolidge (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1903; 1910,; 1965,; undated; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Concert programs and schedules, 1912; 1928,; 1929,; undated (Box 21)
  - Correspondence by others
    - Schweitzer, Louis to Hélène Bresslau, Mar. 13, 1912 (Box 21)
    - Schweitzer, Louisa to Hélène Schweitzer, Dec. 28, 1926 (Box 21)
    - Von Halen, Luise to Margaret Von Schubert, 1963 (Box 21)
  - Manuscripts by others
    - "Les Deux Frères" by Nikos Kazantzakis, autograph typescript (2 copies) (Box 21)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits of Albert Schweitzer
      - "Night Rounds" by Erica Anderson, and bearing her signature (Box 21)
      - Lambaréné, with Albert Schweitzer signature, 1944 (Box 21)
      - Printed portraits (2), each with Albert Schweitzer signature, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Portraits (4), no signatures (Box 21)
      - Portrait of Schweitzer mounted with scene of Lambaréné, by Erica Anderson, and bearing her signature, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Scenes of Lambaréné (Box 21)
      - Printed portrait of Carl Ludwig Schleich with holograph note by Albert Schweitzer (Box 21)
  - Printed material
    - "Contrepoint et Harmonie" A. Dommel-Diény (Box 21)
    - "Mission du Congo Français sur les Rives de l'Ogooué" inscribed "À ma fille Rhéna. Albert Schweitzer Lambarènè", 28_6_1961 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Class schedules from Strassburg, 1906-1908; undated (Box 21)
    - List of students and their fees (Box 21)
    - Map of Lambaréné with Albert Schweitzer signature, 1954 (Box 21)
    - Pi Kappa Lambda membership certificate and pin, 1948 (Box 21)
    - Themes for the theological "Staatsexamen", 1896 (Box 21)
    - Miscellany (Box 21)
    - Mahogany box inscribed "avec mes bonnes pensées Albert Schweitzer" (Oversize 1)